Finding Aid for Virginia R. Allan papers, 1932-1995
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Virginia R. Allan papers 1932-1995
Allan, Virginia R.
1 oversize folders
8.5 linear feet
8517 Aa 2 Ac
Wyandotte, Michigan, businesswoman, chairwoman of the President's Task Force on Women's Rights and Responsibilities during the Nixon Administration, later deputy assistant secretary of state for public affairs. Papers and photographs relating to her interest in women's rights, the equal rights amendment, Republican Party politics, the activities of International Women's Year, 1975, and the National Federation of Business and Professional Women's Clubs.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection was donated in several different accessions by Virginia R. Allan (donor no. 5667 ).
No further additions to the papers are expected.
The collection is open to research.
Virginia R. Allan has had a distinguished career as an educator, business woman, civic leader, and national and international stateswoman. Born October 21, 1916 in Wyandotte, Michigan, Allan earned her A.B. and M.A. degrees from the University of Michigan in 1939 and 1945, respectively, graduating Phi Beta Kappa. Her education prepared her to be an educator and, with the exception of a year spent on a World War II assembly line, it was as a teacher of English in the Dearborn and Detroit school systems that Allan devoted the first part of her career. A well respected and innovative educator, Allan pioneered the Job Upgrading Program, which was designed to help drop-outs return to school or otherwise find meaningful employment. After establishing four job upgrading centers, Allan in 1953 was appointed assistant principal of Redford High School. In 1955, she left teaching to become co-owner and executive vice-president of Cahalan Drug Stores, Inc. in Wyandotte.
As a teacher and businesswoman, Allan developed an interest in local and state affairs, and during the early 1960s became especially active in the National Federation of Business and Professional Women's Clubs, serving in a series of increasingly responsible positions, as membership chairman, third, second, and first vice-president, and in 1964, as national president. With the BPW, Allan became a vocal advocate of women's rights, supporting and encouraging the role of women in the business world. She helped organize the National Federation's Young Career Women's Program, participated in numerous women's leadership conferences, and originated the concept of a nationwide network of State Commissions on the Status of Women. In addition to her BPW work, Allan in 1964 was appointed Regent of Eastern Michigan University, a position she held for ten years.
In 1969, Allan was named chair of President Nixon's Task Force on Women's Rights and Responsibilities and also served eight years on the Citizens' Advisory Council on the Status of Women. In 1972, she was appointed Deputy Assistant Secretary of State for Public Affairs where she served until the beginning of the Carter Administration. During her five years in the Department of State, Allan was a strong proponent of human rights, especially the rights of women, both nationally and internationally. In her official capacity she helped found and support the National Commission on the Observance of International Women's Year (1975) and the Decade for Women (1975-85). This was part of her more general responsibility to foster public/private cooperation in U.S. foreign relations. Allan served both as liaison with Nongovernmental Organizations for the International Women's Year Commission, and as member of the First United Nations World Conference for IWY which met in Mexico City in 1975. Allan later attended both the Mid-Decade Conference for Women in 1980 in Copenhagen (as an NGO representative), and the World Conference of the U.N. Decade for Women in Nairobi, Kenya in 1985. Allan was the only person to have attended all three of the UN World Conferences on Women. A tireless worker while in the State Department, Allan was also a delegate to UN Seminars on Women's Economic Participation in their Countries in 1970 in Moscow and in 1973 in Libreville, Gabon.
From 1977 to 1983, Allan accepted a position as special assistant to the dean for women's studies at George Washington University where a scholarship fund in her name was established to promote the study of women's issues. During her years at George Washington University, she organized a series of seminars and fundraisers which focused on the achievements of working women worldwide. In the early 1980s she was also an advocate of gender equality in education as the co-chair of the Citizen's Committee on Women's Education and as the shadow president of National Coalition for Woman and Girls in Education. In the 1980s she was the president of the U.S. Committee for the UN Fund for Women, Inc. (UNIFEM).
Allan has received many honors during her life, including a place in the Michigan Woman's Hall of Fame, which she helped found; honorary doctorates from Olivet College, Eastern Michigan University, and Central Michigan University. She was also a participant in the Old Masters Program at Purdue University in 1964. Today she remains active in local women's and professional affairs.
The Virginia R. Allan Papers have been grouped both according to types of documents covering her entire career (biographical, correspondence, writings and speeches, etc.). These are followed by three series of files pertaining to Allan's activities and organizational affiliations within specific time periods in her career. These chronological divisions (with some overlapping of dates) are 1950s-1972, 1971-1977, and 1977-1985. Although each of these chronological series documents Allan's life-long interest in women's issues, there are obvious highlights to each. The first chronological series - 1950s-1972, is especially solid with material relating to Allan's association with the Michigan and the National Federation of Business and Professional Women, and her service on the President's Task Force on Women's Rights and Responsibilities. The second of these series - 1971-1977 - obviously documents Allan's work at the State Department, her role with the International Women's Year and her participation in the Mexico City Conference in 1975. And the third chronological series - 1977-1985 - contain files pertaining to her participation in the second and third United Nations International Women's Conferences and to her faculty responsibilities at George Washington University.
The collection concludes with a small series -- Groups and Activities -- which contains both material dated after 1985 as well as earlier materials, a series of Personal materials, and a series of Audio-Visual materials that includes photographs, a videotape, and sound recordings.
Subjects:
Allan, Virginia R.; Women's rights--United States.; Equal Rights Amendments--United States.; United States--Politics and government--1974-1977.; United States--Politics and government--1969-1974.; Wyandotte (Mich.); National Federation of Business and Professional Women's Clubs.; Nixon, Richard M. (Richard Milhous), 1913-1994.; Republican Party (Mich.); United States. Dept. of State.; United States. President's Task Force on Women's Rights and Responsibilities.; International Women's Year, 1975.; Women--Political activity--United States.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Allan, Virginia R.; Ford, Betty, 1918-2011.; Ford, Gerald R., 1913-2006.; National Federation of Business and Professional Women's Clubs.; Politicians--Michigan.; Politicians' spouses--Michigan.; United States. President's Task Force on Women's Rights and Responsibilities.; Women.; Women's rights.
Subjects - Sound Recordings:
Allan, Virginia R.; Equal Rights Amendments--United States.; National Federation of Business and Professional Women's Clubs.; Businesswomen.; Women--Political activity--United States.
Contributors: Sound Recordings
Griffiths, Martha W. (Martha Wright), 1912-2003.; Reunes, Aris.
Genre Terms:
Photographs.; Sound recordings.
- Biographical/personal
  - Biographical Information (Box 1)
  - Awards, Citations, Honorary Degrees (Box 1)
  - Michigan Women's Hall of Fame
    - Election of VA 1985 (Box 1)
    - Programs and speeches introducing other inductees 1987-1988 (Box 1)
  - Education (Box 1)
  - Teaching career (Box 1)
  - Newspaper Clippings 1962-1995, 6 folders (Box 1)
  - Travels
    - Trip to Alaska 1935 (Box 1)
    - Trip to Germany To View Success of Marshall Plan 1967 (Box 1)
    - Trip to Paris with Ladies' Home Journal, 1971 (Box 1)
- Correspondence
  - 1963-1995, 12 folders (Box 1)
- Writings, speeches, etc.
  - Speeches 1964-1989, 5 folders (Box 1)
  - Articles and published interviews 1975-1995 (Box 2)
  - Articles about VA 1985-1995 (scattered) (Box 2)
  - Working files (including draft) of proposed volume to be written by VA, Margaret E. Galey, and others and entitled "Women and Politics in the United Nations" with chapters on the International Women's Year and the Mexico City Conference 1989-1995, 1 folders (Box 2)
  - Interview 1991 with VA conducted by Elayne Clift for proposed MS article entitled "Mentors and Models: Four outstanding feminists who helped shape a political agenda" (Box 2)
- Activities\Organizational Responsibilities 1950s-1972 1960s-1971
  - Ad Hoc Committee on Women's Rights and Responsibilities in International Affairs 1971 (Box 2)
  - Eastern Michigan University 1971-1974 (Box 2)
    VA was a member of the Board of Regents
  - Health, Education and Welfare, Dept. of
    - General 1973 (Box 2)
    - Women's Action Program 1971-1972, 2 folders (Box 2)
    - Special Consultant to the Secretary on Women's Rights and Responsibilities 1971-1972 (Box 2)
  - Intercollegiate Association of Women Students 1970-1971, 4 folders (Box 2)
  - Job upgrading-Detroit Public Schools 1949-1960, 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Labor Department 1971 (Box 2)
  - Michigan Political Caucus 1971 (Box 2)
  - Michigan Federation of BPW
    - Clippings circa 1950s-1968 (Box 2)
    - Bulletins 1960-1963 (Box 2)
    - Speech 1957 (Box 2)
  - National Federation of Business and Professional Women's Clubs
    - Committee Files 1960-1964 (Box 2)
    - Convention Files 1960-1962 (Box 2)
    - Convention Files 1963-1973 (Box 3)
    - Board of Directors Files 1959-1970 (Box 3)
    - Board of Trustees Files 1961-1968 (Box 3)
    - Topical Files 1954-1972
      - Annual Reports 1955-1962 (Box 3)
      - Biographical material (Box 3)
      - Bulletins 1962-1964 (Box 3)
      - Chinese Nursing Home 1961-1962 (Box 3)
      - Congress of Business and Professional Women's Clubs in San Salvador 1972 (Box 3)
        (includes photos)
      - Election to Presidency, correspondence 1963 (Box 3)
      - ERA National Day of Celebration 1978 (Box 3)
      - Gwen Frostic Plaque 1982 (Box 3)
      - Miscellaneous (Box 3)
      - National Business Women's Week 1963 (Box 3)
      - National Motorcade October 5-12, 1963 (Box 3)
      - President's activity report 1964 (Box 3)
      - 75th Anniversary Task Force 1989-1994 (Box 3)
      - Strategic and Long Range Planning Committee 1982-1984 (Box 3)
      - United Nations and international file 1964-1965 (Box 3)
      - Women in Transition Projects 1985-1986 (Box 3)
  - Citizen's Advisory Council on the Status of Women 1971 (Box 4)
  - National Organization for Women 1971 (Box 4)
  - National Women's Political Caucus 1971-1972, 5 folders (Box 4)
  - President's Task Force on Women's Rights and Responsibilities, 7 folders (Box 4)
  - Old Master's Program (Purdue University) 1964 (Box 4)
  - Society for Advancement of Management (SAM)-Women in Business (Box 4)
  - United Nations Survey on the Status of Women and Family Planning 1971 (Box 4)
  - United Nations Seminar on the Participation of Women in Economic Life (Libreville, Republic of Gabon) July-August 1971 (Box 4)
    (VA was Observer)
  - United Nations Seminar on the Participation of Women in the Economic Life of their Countries, Moscow 1970, 2 folders (Box 4)
  - Women United 1971, 2 folders (Box 4)
  - Women's Education for Delegate Selection 1972, 4 folders (Box 4)
  - Women's Movement (general) (Box 4)
- Activities/Organizational Responsibilities 1971-1977 1972-1976
  - Deputy Assistant Secretary of State for Public Affairs 1972-1976 Chronological files
    - March 1972-July 1973, 3 folders (Box 4)
    - August 1973-December 1976, 7 folders (Box 5)
    - Daily notes (Box 5)
  - Deputy Assistant Secretary of State for Public Affairs 1972-1976 Topical files
    - Bureau of Public Affairs 1973-1975 (Box 5)
    - Center of Concern: Women and World Economics/Mary P. Burke 1976 (Box 5)
    - Citizens Advisory Council on the Status of Women, 16 folders (Box 5)
    - Equal Rights Amendment 1972-1973 (Box 6)
    - Equal Rights Amendment Congressional Jubilee Banquet 1972 (Box 6)
    - Hemispheric Conference for Women '76 1976 (Box 6)
    - Institute of Personnel Management 1972-1973 (Box 6)
    - Inter-American Commission of Women 1972-1973 (Box 6)
    - International Women's Year, United Nations World Conference of the, Mexico City June 19, 1975-July 2, 1975
      - Correspondence and Short Reports 1972-1977, 2 folders (Box 6)
      - General, 16 folders (Box 6)
      - Development of Plans for the Observance of IWY 1973-1974 (Box 6)
      - Planning 1973 (Box 6)
      - Planning 1974 (Box 6)
      - Regional Conference on Interdependence and International Women's Year, Chicago 1974 (Box 6)
      - Executive Orders/White House Press Releases 1974-1976 (Box 6)
      - Secretariat/Communications Network 1973-1976 (Box 6)
      - Seminar of Experts 1974 (Box 6)
      - Progress Reports to A. Armstrong, Counselor to the President 1973-1974 (Box 6)
      - Working Committee 1975 (Box 6)
      - Workshop at Foreign Policy Conference for Nongovernmental Organizations (NGOs) 1973 (Box 6)
      - United States Center
        - Developmental Funding 1973-1975 (Box 6)
        - Advisory Committee 1974-1975 (Box 6)
      - World Conference Planning 1975-1976 (Box 6)
      - Mexico City World Conference 1975 (Box 6)
      - Commemorative Stamp 1973-1975 (Box 6)
      - United Nations Official Emblem 1974-1975 (Box 6)
      - National Commission
        - Notes 1976 (Box 6)
        - Publications/Fund-raising 1976 (Box 6)
        - Administration/Funding 1976 (Box 6)
      - News Releases 1972-1975 (Box 6)
    - Occupational and Personnel Materials 1972-1977 (Box 7)
    - Organisation for Economic Co-operation and Development meeting of experts 1973-1975 (Box 7)
    - President's Commission on White House Fellowships 1973-1975 (Box 7)
    - State Department miscellanea (Box 7)
    - United Nations (proposed seminar) 1973 (Box 7)
    - United Nations Economic Committee (UNEC)/UN Commission on the Status of Women 1973-1974 (Box 7)
    - Visit of Leaders of Non Governmental Organizations to Brussels 1972 (Box 7)
    - Visit 1975 U.S. Women NGO Leaders Visit to NATO, 2 folders (Box 7)
    - White House Fellows 1972-1973 (Box 7)
    - Women's Issues (miscellaneous) (Box 7)
- Activities\Organizational Responsibilities 1977-1985
  - George Washington University, Women's Studies
    - Correspondence 1978-1979 (Box 7)
    - Committee for the Dove Foundation (Box 7)
    - General Information (Box 7)
    - Grant Renewal Proposal 1980 (Box 7)
    - Notebook 1977 (Box 7)
    - Proposals (Box 7)
    - Seminars and Programs 1978-1980 (Box 8)
    - Women in the World Committee (Box 8)
    - Women in the World Programs 1977-1979, 3 folders (Box 8)
    - Val Kill Planning Meeting 1978 (Box 8)
    - Virginia Allan Fund for Full Partnership (Box 8)
  - Citizen's Council on Women's Education 1982-1984, 2 folders (Box 8)
  - National Coalition for Women and Girls in Education 1984 (Box 8)
  - UN Second World Conference on Women-Copenhagen 1980, 2 folders (Box 8)
  - UN Third World Conference on Women-Nairobi 1985
    - Business and Professional Women's Clubs NGO Reports
      - National Consultative Committee 1984-1985 (Box 8)
      - Correspondence (Box 8)
      - Grants (Box 8)
      - Meeting Materials, 2 folders (Box 8)
      - Planning Papers (Box 8)
    - Notes, 2 folders (Box 8)
- Groups and Activities (later materials)
  - Business and Professional Women's Club
    - National Convention, Program, script 1988 (Box 8)
    - Long Range Planning Meeting, scripts, speeches, notes, correspondence 1984 (Box 8)
    - National Women's Business Week 1983, 1988, 2 folders (Box 8)
    - International Conference, program, speech 1964 (Box 8)
  - ERA Presidential Task Force, report, drafts with notes, House of Representatives Subcommittee testimony 1969-1971 (Box 8)
  - International Women's Year, Civil Service Journal Article 1975 (Box 8)
  - Miscellaneous correspondence (Box 8)
  - Unifem, correspondence and newsletters (Box 8)
  - . (Box 8)
- Personal
  - Awards, honorary degrees, congratulatory correspondence (Box 8)
  - Biographies, resumes, newsclippings (Box 8)
  - Cahalan Drug Stores, newsclippings, correspondence (Box 8)
  - Correspondence, to V.A. largely with references to her accomplishments, from notable people (Box 8)
  - Family, correspondence, newsclippings, funeral programs (Box 8)
  - Teaching in Michigan, Cooley High, Detroit yearbook, with notations from students 1949 (Box 8)
  - "On to Alaska," manuscript and preamble (Box 8)
- Audio-Visual material
  - Photographs
    - Portraits (including baby pictures) (Box 9)
    - VA with presidents and other public figures (Box 9)
    - Advisory Council on the Status of Women (Box 9)
    - Business and Professional Women Club
      - General and miscellaneous subjects (Box 9)
      - Meetings of Detroit No. 3 chapter 1950s (Box 9)
      - National Motorcade 1963 and Detroit reception (Box 9)
      - Illinois Convention (Box 9)
      - Philadelphia Convention (Box 9)
      - With Senator Margaret Chase Smith (Box 9)
    - Deputy Assistant Secretary of State for Public Affairs
      - Swearing-in ceremony March 3, 1972 (Box 9)
      - Women's Involvement Exhibition 1974 (Box 9)
    - Eastern Michigan University (Box 9)
      (receiving honorary degrees, with members of the Board of Regents, etc.)
    - International Women's Conference, Copenhagen 1980 (Box 9)
    - International Women's Year 1975 (Box 9)
    - Michigan Women's Hall of Fame 1985 (Box 9)
    - Miscellaneous and unidentified (Box 9)
      (mainly VA at BPW and State Department functions)
    - President's Task Force on Women's Rights (under Richard Nixon) (Box 9)
    - University of Michigan (honorary degree?) (Box 9)
    - Miscellaneous later photos (Box 9)
    - Slides; folder includes BPW convention Dallas 1963 at which VA was installed as national president; also images taken during trips to China and Taiwan (Box 9)
  - Videotape (VHS): Veteran Feminists of America 1994 (Box 9)
  - Audio-tapes, 2 audiocassettes; 3 audiotapes reel-to-reel tapes
    - Recording of State Department swearing-in ceremony 1972 (Box 9)
    - Speech 1974 of Martha Griffiths before the Chicago convention of the National Federation of Business and Professional Women's Clubs on the Equal Rights Amendment (Box 9)
    - Tape on Commission on the Status of Women (Box 9)
    - Interview with Aris Reunes 1971 (Box 9)